Jane? You in there?
- I'm up. I'm up.
- Homicide in San Francisco.
Cho and Rigsby are already
on their way.
Did you sleep here?
No, I was working.
It looks like you were sleeping.
Well, I programmed my, uh, dreams
to work on the Red John case.
Oh, well, then make sure
you put in for overtime.
Ah, healthy skepticism.
I like it. But it could work.
Mendeleev saw the entire
periodic table in his dream.
That's nice for him.
- Jane? As a friend...
- Shall we?
This doesn't look good.
Keeps me going.
"There's evidence
of a physical confrontation"
and this is where
he ended up.
He was on his back
when the shots were fired.
Eight to ten rounds to the head.
- What head?
- Yeah.
Two motel guests heard
muffled pops around 1:00 A.M.
figured it was city traffic.
No defense wounds. You'd think
he would've at least put up his hands
- to shield his face.
- Well, it depends how hard he fell.
Forensics recovered the casings.
9 millimeter.
Also collected a cigarette butt
and some red fibers
around the body.
You woke me for this?
This man is a sociopath.
He should've been in prison.
He was.
Full pardon two days ago.
Name's Henry Dahl.
Convicted nine years ago
in the rape and murder
of one Jennie Winter.
Was a lifer at Del Norte
until a new DNA test set him free.
- How'd you peg him as an inmate?
- Give me a break.
A classic rooster build...
massive upper body, skinny legs.
Jaundiced skin
probably hepatitis C
from the dirty needle tattoo
on his elbow.
Spiderweb representing
the passage of time.
Wh-where are you going?
I'm tired, and I don't really care
who killed this creep.
He was innocent.
He made instruments
of death out of toothpicks.
I know you, don't I?
Are you with homicide?
Right now I'm with you
unless, uh, of course...
Are you with homicide?
Did you know it cost taxpayers
2.4 million
to convict Henry Dahl
in the murder of Jennie Winter?
No kidding.
That's a lot of money.
Now they'll have to spend millions
more finding and convicting Dahl's killer
because the state set
a hardened criminal free.
How many man hours will you waste
chasing Henry Dahl's killer?
Not too many.
- Anything usable?
- Eh... maybe.
Get this.
"And I'm here to tell you
Henry Dahl deserved what he got."
"Even the CBI agrees with me... "
"the premiere law enforcement
agency of California."
"Take a look
at one of their agents"
"just two hours after the gruesome
body was discovered"
"in a South San Francisco
motel room."
"Not in too big a rush
to catch the killer, is he?"
"We've identified this man
as Patrick Jane"
"the CBI's top criminal consultant."
"Sleep tight tonight, Mr. Jane.
I know I will."
This isn't unfamiliar territory
to me.
A paid consultant
mistaking state contracts
for a country club
where he can do as he pleases.
He was tired
because he was here all night
working on the Red John case.
It's completely bogus.
Yeah, I know it's bogus.
But that's not how it looks.
It looks like he puked
in the fish tank.
Kinda does, yeah.
The attorney general
has enough to worry about
with the murder
of a wrongly imprisoned man.
I need Jane awake on this.
To be honest, I'm more concerned
about her behavior
than I am about his.
The police never released
Dahl's identity to the press.
So what's a famous cable TV host
doing in front of the motel?
Karen Cross' production company
footed the bill
for Henry Dahl's motel room.
Dahl had driven in from Lodi
to appear as a guest
on her talk show today.
Explains how she knew
he was there.
Wait. Their connection runs
deeper than that.
Before Cross joined Trial TV
she was a State Prosecutor
with 102 violent felony
convictions, no losses.
Guess who one
of those convictions was?
Hello, Dahl-y.
Don't do that.
Why would Dahl appear
on the national talk show
of the lawyer who put him away?
Notoriety. Payback. Women.
Well, Cross can't be happy
about Dahl's name being cleared.
Ruins her perfect record.
Agreed. Jane and I will go
talk to her.
Now did Dahl have
a local residence?
A halfway house in Lodi.
You and Cho, start driving.
See what you find there.
I'll grab the keys.
Hey, what's the matter?
- I had a lunch appointment.
- Well, I can drive to Lodi with Cho.
Oh, no. I couldn't ask you
to do that.
Don't worry about it.
I'll clear it with Lisbon.
You know, you go do
your lunch thing.
I hope you're hungry.
- Hey, Grace.
- Hey.
- Rigsby.
So you should grab a jacket.
I hitched us a ride
on the Tac team chopper.
We're flying to lunch?
TAC team was heading up
north anyhow
so they're gonna drop us off at this
great picnic spot I know on the River.
I mean, you said you had
a couple hours, right?
Yeah. Thank you so much.
I owe you one.
It's okay.
We'll stop for Big Gulps.
How you doing?
You all right?
Eh, it's a little chilly
in here, no?
Excuse me. Hi.
I'm Agent Lisbon.
I think you know my colleague
Patrick Jane.
Well, he's probably taking a nap.
He gets nervous on TV sets.
I imagine so, considering
what happened to his family
after his last talk show appearance.
Even I know better than
to taunt a serial killer on air.
Then you should know better
than to taunt the CBI, because...
I'm a person of interest.
I get it.
So let me make this
easy for you.
Yes, I was outraged
that Henry Dahl was set free.
Did I shoot him? No.
I was in Edit Bay 4
at the time of his murder.
The log includes a contact number
for the editor who was with me.
Why'd you invite Henry
on your show?
The state may have let Henry go
but my show is tougher
than any court of law.
I was gonna nail him
to the cross.
Karen Cross?
You've seen my promos?
Read the trial coverage, too.
It was all smoke and mirrors.
You whipped the jury
into a frenzy
to cover for a lack
of physical evidence.
Two witnesses put Dahl
at the scene.
That doesn't make him
a killer.
You caught a break
when the DNA test from the rape kit
came back as inconclusive.
The new test excludes Dahl
as the perpetrator.
You don't trust DNA?
I don't trust anything coming
outta the justice system.
That's why I left.
I heard you left
because you were gonna be fired
for ethical violations.
Nothing stops me from following
my instincts, Agent Lisbon.
I won't apologize for that.
I spent six months deposing
and questioning Henry.
I'm telling you for a fact
that man was a reptile.
Ooh tea!
- Shrink, right?
- Excuse me?
The vest.
The tea.
Karen Cross
always invites a shrink
to comfort the grieving mother.
I'm Jodi Dahl.
I'm sorry for your loss.
Don't you worry about me.
I've been letting go
of Henry for years.
Excuse me, hon.
Tea?
It's a hug in a... cup.
No, no, thank you.
I take it you're family, too.
Max Winter.
The widower of the victim.
True victim.
My wife's name was Jennie.
There is nothing about you
that indicates loss.
No scars of aged pain.
Bravo.
Corner seat says you're wary.
Need to control your environment.
In most people
that creates tension.
But your breathing is relaxed.
What's your trick, Max?
It's... inner peace.
The kind of peace you get
when you shoot your wife's killer?
Henry was innocent it seems.
Well, if that's true the man
that raped and cut your wife up
is still out there.
That doesn't bother you?
Jennifer's life ended abruptly.
Could've been a drunk driver
could've been a meteorite.
Anger is unhelpful
and unproductive.
Well, I don't know.
Some people... it's, uh
it's invigorating.
I'm sorry I don't fit your image
of the tragic husband.
You ask where my peace
comes from.
It's called reconciliation.
I can't undo what happened
to my wife
but for the sake
of my son Jackson
I can decide how I wanna
live thereafter.
So I forgive Henry...
Or... whoever it was
who killed Jennie.
I actually forgave them
long ago.
Let's get you wired for sound
Mr. Winter.
Excuse me.
- Where's miss Dahl?
- "Right at stage four."
Okay. Bring her to the stage.
This was the scene
nine years ago
when Henry Dahl was attacked
before a pretrial hearing
by the husband
of the woman whose throat
he was accused of cutting.
"I'm gonna kill you, Dahl."
"What're you doing?"
"Three deputies were guarding
Henry Dahl that day."
"Now that was the Max I knew."
He would be dancing a jig
after hearing Henry Dahl was dead.
But am I to understand
you actually forgave Dahl
before this so-called new
DNA evidence came to light?
"It's called reconciliation, Karen."
- "Reconciliation?"
- "Yeah, reconciliation. In my case... "
"Oh, I'm familiar
with what reconciliation means."
"Reconciliation is basically
when family members of victims"
"they waltz over to the prison"
"they decide they're gonna forgive
this person"
"who murdered
their wife or children."
"I just don't buy it, Max."
"He was only here for two nights.
I hardly saw him."
"When I did, he was just so happy
to be free. Who wouldn't be?"
Did Mr. Dahl have any visitors?
Yeah, the first night out.
Some woman... she dropped by
for a few hours.
Not bad-looking either.
The guy didn't waste much time.
- You catch her name?
- No. Sorry. Here we go.
- Thank you.
- Thanks a lot.
Oh, we can take it from here.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Well, someone was looking
for something.
Thank you
Captain obvious.
Three hours of brooding silence
then sarcasm.
It's like we're married.
Sorry, Cho. It's just special
Agent Craig O'Laughlin
and his... chopper.
What's she see
in that guy anyway?
Ivy League degree in criminology
6 years
in the 101st Airborne
and a black belt in Wushu
from a real Shaolin Temple.
Yeah, thanks, buddy.
Whatever.
Cho, under the bed!
- What are you doing?
- Just go! Go!
Bet they don't teach that
at a Shaolin Temple.
"Dad! In the garage!"
Wow. Hi.
I thought you were my dad.
No.
What...
an amazing phenomenon...
flying machines frozen...
In mid-air.
I kinda feel sorry for 'em.
Did... did you do all this?
Um, no, my... my dad does.
I just help out.
You're Max's son.
I-I saw you at the talk show.
Jackson, right?
I-I-I'm... I'm looking
for your dad.
Who are you?
- You... you a cop or something?
- No. Too many laws to uphold.
But I-I do work
with the police.
Don't touch that, please.
It's... it's not cured yet.
It feels okay to me.
It needs two more hours.
Can... can you go now?
Uh, look, my... my dad's
not at the house.
I don't know where he is.
Sure, you do.
You just don't want me to know.
Is he hiding something?
No, he's not hiding anything.
- Are you?
- No. Of course not.
Your dad doesn't seem like
the kind of man
who would ask you to lie.
Artie Mock.
"Multiple arrests
for assault, battery"
"battery with injury..."
And today, aggravated assault
against a police officer.
I'm sorry.
- Did I hurt you?
- It was just a mattress.
Now what's your relationship
with Henry Dahl?
Friends.
We met in junior college.
- We were art majors.
- Why'd you break into his room?
I was looking for my money.
He owes me 22 large
plus nine years' interest.
Where were you last night?
Last night?
I was working graveyard
at the plant.
And, no, I didn't kill him.
I mean, now I ain't ever
gonna see what's mine.
What did Dahl owe you for?
Statute of limitations on drug
dealing is what, six years?
Six years.
In that case, Henry and I ran
a small business in college.
We... we weren't very good
at art
so we started
distributing cocaine.
- That's a natural transition.
- That's what we said.
No, H-Henry was storing
a shipment
and... and he gets popped
for murder.
Two kilos.
I visited him in prison
and he tells me
that the... the stash gets
confiscated, so I let it go.
But then the day
that Henry gets outta prison
he starts flossing about taking
his girlfriend to Jamaica
so I'm thinking... he's still got
those drugs hidden.
- His girl?
- Mm-hmm.
Henry'd been out for two days.
When'd he find a girlfriend?
She found him, in prison.
They were pen pals.
According to Del Norte
Henry Dahl had just one name
on his approved e-mail list...
a woman named Betsy Meyers
from Lodi, his hometown.
Lodi... yeah, I was just there today.
Long drive. Hot.
She and Dahl had a thing going
in high school.
She reached out to him
two months ago
rekindled their romance.
But there's just one problem.
- Betsy's married?
- Yes, to a Sean Meyers.
He's a factory worker.
They've been together
for seven years.
- Somebody should question him.
- Agreed.
Someone who hasn't been
to Lodi yet.
I wanna see how willingly
they come to us.
Let's call them in in the morning.
In the meantime,
there's no shortage of suspects
who hated Henry Dahl.
23 people threatened his life
during his murder trial
most of which were friends
or family of the alleged victim.
Here's a list of those names
courtesy of our cable
television friend, Miss Cross.
We got a lotta eyes on us
on this one.
I want you to stay late
and run down these names.
Bravo.
Oh.
I had a feeling
I'd see you again.
Takes a confident man
to visit a shooting range
when he's still
a murder suspect.
Or an innocent one.
I never got your name.
- Sorry?
- Never got your name.
- Uh, Patrick Jane.
- What kinda gun do you use, Patrick?
Oh, no.
I don't... I don't use.
No? That's, uh, a little strange
for a policeman, isn't it?
Me, I-I like
a well-balanced .45...
best combination of power
accuracy, and kick.
- Hey, hey. Careful. Whoa.
- Whoa.
- Whoa, watch the muzzle sweep.
- Sorry.
You never point at anything
you don't wanna shoot.
So...
How can I help you, Patrick?
Well, um, I'm just curious
to hear how you did it.
How I did what?
Forgave your wife's killer.
- Ah. So you believe me now.
- Well, don't get carried away
but I-I did find out
that you've become quite the, uh...
evangelist for reconciliation
corporate talks and all.
You know why I came here
in the first place?
I manage real estate funds.
I never touched a weapon
in my life.
But then Jennie was butchered
and I needed a release.
At first, I pretended
the targets were Henry Dahl
and now, they're just targets.
It's a discipline.
Very Zen.
You found the gift of forgiveness
through firearms.
Yeah, shooting helped me cope.
My son led me to forgiveness.
All this rage inside me
that lust for vengeance...
I could see
I was scaring Jackson.
I didn't wanna lose him too.
Lo and behold
Henry Dahl was exonerated
like a sign from above.
Yes. Exactly. I just wish
I had forgiven him sooner.
Do you have children, Patrick?
No.
Try it.
No better pain relief.
- I'm not in pain.
- No?
I sense pain.
Ah, it's nothing a gun will fix.
By the way
I don't own the gun.
I just rent them
while I'm here.
And I was with my son, at home
at the time of the murder.
Just, uh...
In case you're interested.
It's gonna get loud.
I'll just step back here.
Henry had a beautiful spirit.
That whole bad boy thing...
that was always just an act.
He even wanted to try acting
when he got outta prison.
How did you know that?
He told me...
in his e-mails.
Did you know that your wife
was exchanging e-mails
with a convicted felon?
Yeah, I was taking dictation for her.
What do you think? No.
Betsy, according to the prison
you'd been writing Henry
for two months.
- Why'd you reach out to him?
- Yeah, why did you?
You've had a first love, right?
"You know that feeling?"
"It never really goes away
not totally."
I never thought
that Henry killed anyone
and when I read that there was
new DNA evidence
I just wanted to say
"Woot, woot," you know
as a friend.
Does this sound like friends?
"Dear Henry
wild thoughts in my head."
"I know I shouldn't wonder
what your body feels like now"
- "but it's all I... "
- Okay, stop. All right?
Why are you doing this to me?
My husband is sitting right here.
I'm sorry.
"I'm so sorry."
She is so full of it.
What? She wrote some stuff to a guy.
There's worse crimes.
"Betsy, tell me the truth."
- You heard. She's in love with him.
- No, that's not true!
I really just started
writing him as a friend.
We were arguing so much.
And he knew me so well.
"He started saying
all the things to me"
"that you stopped saying
years ago."
"Did you have any contact
with him after he was released?"
"No. Only in e-mails."
Betsy, we showed a photo
of you to the manager
of the halfway house
Henry was living in.
"He identified you as the woman
who visited Henry"
"the day after his release."
"You slept with him?"
- Oh, hush.
- I didn't say anything.
What is this, marriage counsel?
They're suspects
in the shooting.
These two?
Really? Hmm.
Um...
- Can I see your gun?
- Hmm?
Where were the 2 of you
at 1:00 A.M.?
Drinking beers at the Lamplighter.
Hi. Patrick Jane.
Very nice to meet you.
- Hold that, please.
- Whoa.
- What?
- I'm sorry. Here.
- What the hell are you doing?
- It's okay. Rigsby took the bullets out.
Muzzle sweeps. They have
no idea how to handle a gun.
Give me a break.
"Van Pelt, run down
Betsy and Sean's alibis."
You, outside!
Excuse me.
So you're a gun expert now?
No, not me. Max Winter.
You should see him shoot.
- Did he shoot Dahl?
- What caliber was the murder weapon?
- 9 millimeter.
- Yeah, Max prefers a .45.
Oh, shucks.
I guess he's innocent.
Here's a revised suspect list.
Max is still on it.
And I hope you got
some sleep last night
because we're going to Lodi
to run interviews.
I just got back from Lodi.
Van leaves in 20 minutes.
Be outside.
Patrick Jane.
I didn't recognize you yesterday
at the crime scene.
You were quite the psychic once.
Oh, there's no such thing
as psychics.
So you say now.
Your cold reading of a serial killer
on live television
led to the brutal murder
of your wife and daughter.
Oh. Really?
Thanks for reminding me.
Mr. Jane, I am on your side.
You were a victim
of violent crime
and now you help others.
That's wonderful.
Don't tell me you don't have
the psychic stuff.
What are you doing for the CBI
if you're not psychic?
Are you scamming them
Mr. Jane?
No, Karen, I am not.
Well, prove it.
Identify Dahl's killer.
Well, if I had carte blanche
to do things my way
I would do just that, but they don't
give me carte blanche.
The CBI won't, but I will.
Deputy?
You've been served.
You're hereby commanded to testify
before a studio audience of your peers.
What do you need
to solve this crime?
Name it.
Well, I suppose, uh...
I need the help of those
that are affected by Dahl's murder.
Those two you had on your show
yesterday would do.
I'll bring them back.
And, uh, I guess
uh, I need suspects.
Yeah. Make sure these people
are in the audience.
Give 'em an appearance fee
whatever it takes.
Beats driving back to Lodi.
"You saw him here first...
the sleeping CBI Agent."
"Well, get ready to meet him."
"Patrick Jane... psychic detective?
Tragic victim?"
"You be the judge today at 3:00"
"when Mr. Jane taps
his mind's eye"
"to reveal who killed Henry Dahl."
This is good?
Well, where is he?
We're five minutes to air.
Without him, it's just
a rehash of yesterday's show.
I've left messages everywhere.
Oh.
Oh. Sorry I'm late. I had to stop
by a Bed and Bath Boutique.
Mr. Jane, there is a reason
that I asked you
to arrive two hours early.
I need to walk you through
the lineup.
- Are all my suspects here?
- Yeah, they're in the first two rows.
Now the lineup... I'll start
with my state of the union
and then we're just gonna roll a clip
- to introduce you.
- A clip?
Uh, y... well
just some old footage.
- My Red John talk show appearance.
- Oh, no.
Just save... save
your reaction for on-air.
I really want you
to relive the moment...
Excuse me, Karen.
I gotta hand out candles.
Candles? Wait.
What... what candles?
Hey, folks.
I hope Lodi is treating you well.
A little treat from Karen Cross.
Hand them out. One each.
Here you go. Pass that back
to him, please. Thank you.
Ah, Jackson.
Here to see the old man again
are you? Here.
Have a candle.
We need you onstage now.
Oh, I have to hand these out.
They're for my act.
Unless, uh, what are you doing?
Everybody must have one.
Okay?
I need these. Thank you.
- Patrick.
- Max.
You've probably read stories
about psychics who help
the police solve murder cases.
Well, today, we're gonna take
a peek behind the mystic's veil
to see how that's done.
To introduce our featured guest
we have a dramatic video clip
of his last talk show.
Uh, Karen, sorry to interrupt.
Uh, Mr. Jane, I'll get to you
in a minute.
Could you please sit down?
You... you... you wanted to tell me
something about the lineup.
I forget. The lineup...
did you tell me?
The lineup, I forget.
Forget the lineup.
What is the lineup?
- Uh... I'm...
- Let me remind you.
Ladies and gentlemen
it is time to unmask the shooter.
What you have all
just witnessed
is a remarkable piece
of mental tomfoolery
"from our psychic guest star
Patrick Jane."
However, this is not
Mr. Jane's show
so I'm gonna ask Mr. Jane again
to please sit down.
I'm sorry. I forget. Whose show is it?
Whose show? I forget.
I forget whose show.
Forget...
W-will you stop doing that?
You are a guest here.
Well, actually, no.
I was, uh, summoned.
Are you sure this is
how you wanna play it?
You really wanna make yourself
a sorrier spectacle?
Oh, is there anyone more sorry
than you, Karen
with your morbid interest in all things
shocking or repulsive?
You pretend to be a victim's advocate
but you're a vulture
preying on the carrion
of human suffering.
Are you gonna give me
that carte blanche
- you promised me or not?
- Yeah, buddy, go.
Yeah.
You gonna give me
that carte blanche?
"I feel like getting me
some carte blanche."
Okay, Mr. Jane
let the psychic wonders unfurl.
There's no such thing
as psychics, Karen.
Only entertainers skilled
in the art of deception.
But I'm happy to, uh, perform
a psychic "demonstration".
Usually begins
with a fantastic claim
such as Henry Dahl's killer
is sitting in this room right now.
And then, uh, any good psychic
would make sure
that the front row
is full of actual police suspects
which I believe that we have done
for you today.
Then he might go on and explain
how, uh, a-a spirit
that has crossed over
still has the power to manipulate
energy in our world...
creating noises, moving objects
and sometimes
even starting fires...
and that is what Henry Dahl
is gonna do for us right now.
Henry Dahl will light a candle
to reveal his shooter.
- Dim the lights, please.
- Oh, I can't wait for this.
That's the spirit.
That's your candle.
Oh. There is one other thing.
A truly world-class psychic
would invite police officials
up on the stage
to make an arrest
once the killer
has been unmasked.
And today
we are very fortunate
to have some, uh, conveniently
telegenic CBI officers...
uh, Agent Wayne Rigsby
and the pocket rocket
the dynamite, heavily armed
cute as a button
Agent Teresa Lisbon.
Ladies and gentlemen
a round of applause.
Ladies and gentlemen, please
raise your candles
high above your heads
while we wait for Henry Dahl
to reveal his shooter.
"Speak to us, Henry."
"Speak to us from beyond"
the great beyond.
This is ridiculous...
- Wait.
- Jackson Winter.
Of course.
Uh, you think it was me?
Henry Dahl was convicted
of killing your mother
but you didn't buy the DNA test
that set him free, did you?
- What are you doing?
- Of course he didn't believe the DNA
I presented an ironclad case.
And the owner of a certain
firing range I visited
tells me that Jackson, in fact
does like to shoot guns.
Prefers a 9 millimeter
same caliber
as the murder weapon.
Look... I didn't shoot anyone, okay?
Dad...
What's more, forensics matched
red fibers from the murder scene
with carpet fibers
from the firing range.
Stop it. You stop this.
My son didn't do anything.
Casting blame on him
like this... it'll ruin his life.
I know.
- Then don't do it.
- Don't let me.
All right.
You leave him alone.
It was me.
I shot Henry Dahl.
Or he is just lying
to protect his son.
- Agents, arrest him.
- I'm not lying.
He's not lying.
His son told me.
What are you talking about?
No, I didn't.
Epoxy takes 12 hours to cure.
Yesterday you told me that
that model
only needed two more hours.
That puts you working in the garage
in the middle of the night.
Your son wasn't asleep.
He heard you leaving. That's why
he wanted to protect you, right?
All right, let him be.
I pulled the trigger
and I can prove it.
You'll find his prints
on the gun.
Ballistics will match the casings.
How did you obtain it?
Gun trafficker, eight years ago.
You purchased an illegal weapon
eight years ago. Why?
Dahl was a lifer
in a state pen.
You had no way of knowing
he'd get out.
Oh, you wanna stop talking now?
That's fine.
All bets are off.
We're gonna take you
and your son into custody.
No, j-just...
Just wait.
I knew Henry was gonna get out
"because I'm the one
who set him free."
How'd you know?
Well, he's a man
of infinite patience
and suppressed rage.
His wife's killer had to die
by his own hand.
He had no choice.
"Okay, you're gonna have
to help me out a little bit."
How did you set Dahl free?
I'm a fund manager
at a real estate investment firm.
I used one fund
to buy up old warehouses...
safe investment
convert 'em into condos...
and that's how my firm came to own
a certain Bay area warehouse
used for evidence storage.
Including DNA.
"It took since months
to pull the condo permits."
"I used that time to gain access
to the property"
and I swapped out
Dahl's DNA sample.
Dahl passes retest.
You kill Dahl.
- You should sell the book rights.
- Hold on.
My client never said
he killed Henry Dahl.
Your client confessed
on basic cable.
To shooting Dahl.
Hello.
I shot that piece of filth.
I shot him right in the face.
But I didn't kill Henry Dahl.
He was already dead.
That's a development.
How do you know Dahl
was dead?
Back of his head
was busted open.
He was lying
in a pool of blood.
- Maybe he was still breathing.
- No.
I checked for a pulse.
I don't buy it.
If you knew Dahl was dead
why'd you shoot him nine times?
Because he murdered my wife.
Uh-oh.
What?
He's telling the truth.
With no head left to speak of
the coroner can't make
a definitely call
but he did say there was less
blood loss than expected
which supports
postmortem gunshots.
Oh, in that case...
Let's go pick up
the actual killer, shall we?
It's kind of obvious now, isn't it?
I mean, shooting is a crime
of planning. That's Max.
He built an entire fleet of planes
with his hands.
- But a blow to the head?
- Crime of passion.
A lot of emotions were flying around
that interrogation room yesterday.
The jilted husband.
Sean Meyers... I felt his pain.
Meyers said he didn't know
his wife was having
an affair with the victim.
Maybe he was lying.
What about his alibi?
He alibi'ed out
for the 1:00 A.M. shooting
but a blow to the head
would've occurred earlier.
It's like watching a symphony orchestra
come together.
Dead River bridge.
Sean Meyers' cell phone server
got a fix on his signal
somewhere around here.
Why would he come out here?
Van Pelt talked
to the apartment manager.
He heard a couple fighting.
Betsy got in her car.
Sean took off after her.
She could be his next victim.
Well, that's one theory.
"Get back!"
- "Betsy!"
- "Stay away from me!"
- "Get over here!"
- Okay.
We're with the CBI.
What's going on here?
Oh, they were up there
when we arrived.
Can't tell yet
but it looks like
an attempted assault.
He's gonna reach her soon.
- "Betsy!"
- We may have to shoot to stop him.
Get back!
Stay away from me!
Betsy!
If you shoot him
you'll have two victims.
She just went up there
to see about jumping.
He's trying to save her.
Can I use that?
Uh, Betsy?
If you're gonna jump
make sure to dive, headfirst.
- Hey.
- Jane.
From that height
you'll just shatter bones
and suffer
massive internal injuries.
Make sure you dive, headfirst.
I just want this all
to end now!
I know.
What do I have to live for?
Um, nothing.
Your husband killed Henry Dahl.
He's going to prison.
You killed Henry?
He was gonna hurt you.
You did that for me, baby?
I got you.
Ah, ain't love grand?
Thank you.
Yeah, she was never
gonna jump anyway.
She just wanted the attention.
I found the e-mails
on her laptop two weeks ago.
My entire world fell apart.
I couldn't lose Betsy.
I just couldn't.
When Henry got out of prison
I went to the motel
but I went to talk with him.
"I'm a free man now."
"Means free love, too."
- "She's married."
- "I'll share her with you."
"I don't mind."
"You learn to share...
in lockdown."
"Where are my damn cigarettes?"
"I'll pay you."
"I'll give you money
to stay away from Betsy."
"How much?"
"I've got 3,200 saved."
"I've got millions coming my way"
"once the state reimburses me
for all that time in jail."
"Sorry."
"I plan on having a little fun
with your wife."
"Maybe I'll..."
"slash her throat..."
"like I did the last one."
"Damn, where are those cigarettes?"
I just wanted to protect her.
This is all my fault.
I'm so sorry.
All right, time to go.
I'll write you every day.
I suppose from your perspective
it's a shame that neither man
will serve any real time.
Oh, will they not?
Well, who knows who really
killed Henry Dahl?
Well, prosecution
will say Sean Meyers.
- He struck him in the head.
- Ah, but did he kill him?
Max may well have lied
to protect himself.
Maybe Dahl was still alive.
Max's attorneys point the finger at Sean
and Sean's attorneys point at Max
and in the end, they both walk.
Yep, that could happen.
Ah, maybe we could save everyone
a lotta time and money
and let 'em both walk now.
After all, the killer did get
what he deserved.
That's common sense.
But, uh, common sense
carries very little weight
in the DA's office.
Pity.
- What you doing there, Rigsby?
- Nothing.
He's trying to light the candle
with the power of his mind.
No, I wasn't.
Is that one of those candles
Jane used on the talk show?
- Look, I know how he did that.
- Oh, yeah?
A candle wick dipped
in liquid phosphorous
will spontaneously
burst into flame when it dries.
The oxygen hits the phosphorous.
Jane must've dipped
the kid's candle in the stuff
before he gave it to him.
Now the real trick, though
is in the timing
which Jane nailed.
Hey. Where are we going
for lunch today?
- Napa.
- Nice.
Bye, guys.
Uh, excuse me, Patrick.
I was looking for you.
It seems they're gonna drop
the attempted murder charge.
The, uh, evidence tampering
is another matter
but my attorney's gonna
work out a deal for probation.
Well, that's...
that's very good for Jackson.
Yeah. I'm told that somebody
high up in your office
was very influential
with the DA.
Mm. Wasn't me.
Good to see you.
Yeah. But I brought you
a gift anyway.
- Oh, listen, thank you but I-I can't...
- Please?
Please.
Okay.
- Should I open it now?
- No.
Was it worth it?
Was what worth it?
The man that killed your wife
no longer exists.
The time you took pursuing him
the pain, the sacrifice...
was it worth it?
Yes, it was.
Thank you.